Personal papers of Sidney E. Chernick
World Bank Group Archives
Personal papers of Sidney E. Chernick
1972 - 1989
WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_95
1.88 linear feet of textual records
World Bank Group Archives
Chernick, Sidney E.
Sidney E. Chernick, a Canadian national, was employed by the World Bank from 1969 to 1990. Chernick graduated from the University of Manitoba and gained a Master's Degree from the University of Toronto and a Ph.D. from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Prior to joining the Bank, Chernick was employed by the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) in Paris, the United Nations Economic Commission for Latin America (ECLA) in Santiago, and, for five years, by the United Nations in New York. He also taught Economics at the University of Melbourne.
Chernick began his employment at the World Bank as an economist in the Central America and Caribbean Department (CAC) in 1969. He was promoted to Senior Economist in 1970.
In 1972 he joined the newly created Policy, Planning and Program Review Department; he would remain in the Department until its termination in 1982. (The Department had different acronyms over the years: EPR from 1972 to 1977 and PPR from 1977 to 1982. It was also referred to as PPPRD and PP&PR.) The basic functions of the PPPRD were to identify development policy issues, to prepare or coordinate analysis of alternative program and policies, and to supervise the presentation of policy papers at the appropriate level of management. It provided guidelines for analysis in economic reports and country programs and reviewed country programs before their submission to the President to ensure the quality of economic analysis, consistency with Bank development objectives, and consideration of alternative strategies.
The PPPRD consisted of only two divisions during its existence: the Policy Planning Division (PPRPP) and the Program Review Division (PPRPR). Chernick was named Division Chief of the Program Review Division in or around September of 1973 and reported directly to PPPRD Director, Hahbub ul Haz. (Ul Haz and the PPPRD, in turn, reported to Hollis B. Chenery, Vice President of the Office of the Vice President Development Policy [DPS].) Chernick's division was responsible for:
* Establishing guidelines for the content of Economic Reports and, in cooperation with the Programming and Budgeting Department, of Country Program Papers
* Managing the review of Economic Reports and Country Program Papers in close collaboration with the Regional Offices and the Programming and Budgeting Department with a view to evaluating alternative policy options for management
* Evaluating the annual and 5-year country economic work program of the Regional Offices
* Maintaining communication links between the DPS and the Regional Offices on issues of development strategy and Bank policy at the country or regional levels
* Analyzing selected economic development issues of Bank-wide relevance and ad hoc questions raised by management; and
* Providing support for selected economic missions.
In the spring of 1976, Chernick was named Senior Advisor in PPPRD and would serve in this capacity until the Bank's and PPPRD's reorganization in 1982. He would also serve as Acting Director at various times during the decade in which he was a PPPRD staff member.
In February of 1982, Chernick was named Assistant Director of the newly-established Country Policy Department (CPD). The CPD replaced the PPPRD and assumed its functions and much of its staff (as well as staff from the former Development Economics Department [DED]). Chernick's main responsibilities in the CPD included:
* Providing advice and support to the regions on designing assistance strategies and preparing CPPs, structural adjustment and other program lending, and carrying out policy dialogue with member countries
* Serving management through reviews of CPPs and country economic and sector work plans, through advice on lending allocation, and through work on operational policy issues
* Conducting applied research and preparing papers on such issues as trade strategies, resource mobilization, economic management, employment productivity and welfare
* Acting as a secretariat for the Operations Policy Sub-Committee of the Managing Committee.
In June 1983, Chernick was named a Senior Advisor of CPD.
In January of 1984, Chernick moved to the South Asia Country Programs Department (ASADR) under the title of Senior Economist. Chernick's activities involved: supporting the design and quality of economic and sector work by undertaking regional, country, and project analyses; and raising the capacity of the practitioners by providing guidance, organizing training courses and regional seminars, and participating actively in recruitment.
On November 1, 1986, Chernick joined the Economic Development Institute (EDI, later the World Bank Institute [WBI]), the Bank's capacity development branch. Chernick was named the Advisor on Senior Policy Seminars in the Institute's Front Office. These seminars, beginning in the mid-1980s, offered short policy-related seminars to high-level government officials that would explore issues, alternatives, and likely implementation problems in bringing about policy improvements. Chernick remained in this position until he retired from the World Bank in 1990.
Published
Fonds consists of Sidney Chernick's chronological files from his time in numerous World Bank departments, including: the Policy, Planning and Program Review Department (PPPRD); Country Policy Department (CPD); South Asia Country Programs Department (ASADR); and the Economic Development Institute (EDI). Chronological files contain few gaps and appear to have functioned as Chernick's personal record of outgoing correspondence.
Chernick originally transferred a single binder of these files to the World Bank's Historian, Jochen Kraske, for consultation. This would suggest about two to three inches of records; however, this was documented in an accession note that provided no specifics regarding which records were in this binder. When Mr. Kraske had finished consulting the binder, he transferred it to the Archives. The rest of the records in this fonds were transferred directly from Chernick to the Archives some years after his retirement from the Bank.
Accruals are not expected.
* See Records of the World Bank Institute ([WB-IBRD/IDA WBI](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-world-bank-institute)), for more records related to the Senior Policy Seminars.
Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
- Policy, Planning and Program Review Department chronological files, 1972 - 1982; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_95-01; 0.84 linear feet of textual records
  Published
  Series consists of chronological files created during Chernick's time as Division Chief, Senior Advisor, and Acting Director of the Policy, Planning and Program Review Department (PPPRD) between 1972 and 1982. Chronological files contain correspondence in different formats; carbon copies of correspondence sent by Chernick are the most common, while paper copies and telexes are also included. The amount of outgoing correspondence, authored by Chernick, is far more substantial than correspondence received byChernick. While much of the correspondence refers to attachments (reports, country program papers [CPPs], meeting minutes, etc.), very few are included in the files.
  Records related to Chernick's role as Division Chief of PPPRD's Program Review Division (PPRPR) from 1973 to 1976 are numerous. The Division's primary roles were to provide guidelines for economic analysis in economic reports and country programs and review CPPs before their submission to the President in order to ensure quality and consistency with the Bank's development objectives. CPPs are confidential reports authored by the regional departments, usually on an annual basis. They include a discussion of a given country's political and economic situation and a history of the Bank's loans and external financing and on that basis propose a five-year lending program for the country. Other, special studies (usually discussing a specific sector within a country or a general development issue) and economic reports were also reviewed by the PPPRD. Chernick's role was to manage his Division's review of CPPs and to arrange Regional Vice Presidents (RVP) meetings and Management Review meetings. As such, correspondence includes: assignment of reviews; schedule of review meetings; discussion of reviews; and policy development and explanation.
  Series also consists of correspondence relating to the development and revision of Operational Manual Statements (OMSs). Assignment of tasks related to OMSs is included as are a small amount of OMS drafts and comments on drafts.
  Records related to a Working Group on Bank/Fund Collaboration are found in this series. This includes Bank President McNamara's initial request for a report. Chernick's role in the research and writing of this report is unclear; he is copied on related correspondence and drafts were sent to him for review.
  Chernick played a significant role in the Development Committee between 1980 and 1982. Created in 1974, the Committee was designed to provide a focal point at a high political level in the structure of economic cooperation for the formation of a comprehensive overview of international activities in the development area, for efficient and prompt consideration of development issues and for coordination of international efforts to deal with problems of financing development. Drafts of Committee meeting agendas are included; in some cases, these drafts are sent from Chernick, as Acting Director of PPPRD, to Bank President McNamara. Correspondence related to scheduling and Committee reviews and projects is also included.
  Records in this series relate to a variety of other topics and activities, including: staff hiring and reviews; staff meetings; mission planning; work programs; conference participation and planning; and policy development related to Structural Adjustment Loans (SALs). Also included are: regular summaries of Board meetings authored by Chernick for Hollis Chenery, Vice President of Development Policy (DPS); ad hoc reports and reviews created by Chernick or his staff for superiors within the Development Policy Vice Presidency (DPS) and externally; comments on reports; and a small amount of correspondence related to the research and publication of Chernick's book The Commonwealth Caribbean: The Integration Experience (1978).
  The original order of the records has been maintained. Records are arranged in chronological order.
  Accruals are not expected.
  * See Records of the Development Committee ([WB IBRD/IDA DC](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-development-committee)).
  Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - November 1981 to May 1982, 1981-11-23 - 1982-05-18; 30066038
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - April to November 1981, 1981-04-01 - 1981-11-23; 30066037
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - October 1980 to March 1981, 1980-10-01 - 1981-03-31; 30066036
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - July to September 1980, 1980-01-07 - 1980-09-30; 01452758
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - 1978, 1978-01-01 - 1978-12-31; 30066034
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - 1977, 1977-01-01 - 1977-12-31; 30066033
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - 1976, 1976-01-01 - 1976-12-31; 30066032
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - December 1974, 1974-12-01 - 1974-12-31; 30066031
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - 1972 to 1974, 1972-08-01 - 1974-02-28; 01452148
- Country Policy Department chronological files, 1982 - 1983; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_95-02; 0.37 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of chronological files created during Chernick's time as Assistant Director of the Country Policy Department (CPD). The type of activities undertaken by Chernick in the CPD was quite similar to those during his years in PPPRD and, consequently, the types of records are also very similar. The majority of the records consist of correspondence in the form of carbon copies, paper copies, and telexes. Nearly all correspondence was authored by Chernick and there is very little incoming correspondence. Reports sometimes accompany correspondence or are included in the files without accompanying correspondence.
  Records relating to country program papers (CPPs) are included in this series, but not in great number. Records generally discuss the scheduling of Regional Vice Presidents (RVP) and Management Review meetings. In addition, Chernick served as Secretariat of the Operations Policy Subcommittee (OPSC). The OPSC was also involved in the review of CPPs and records related to the OPSC in this seriesdiscuss this activity.
  Series also consists of regular status reports on Structural Adjustment Lending (SAL) and Program Lending (PL) operations. Other SAL-related records are included, such as Proposed Structural Adjustment Loan and Related Technical Assistance Project reports and SAL Progress Reports.
  Between 1982 and 1983, Chernick was on the Steering Group Committee for the Bank's 'Pioneers' of development economics lecture series. His responsibilities included booking guests/speakers, making announcements, booking rooms, and planning Steering Group Committee meetings. Records related to these activities are included in this series.
  Records in this series also relate to a variety of other topics and activities, including: seminar attendance and planning; Department retreat planning; and publication of country Economic Memoranda. Other records include: Terms of Reference for Country and Economic and SAL Supervision missions; comments by Chernick on reports and project proposals; Country Economic and Sector Work quality control reports; and administrative and staffing records.
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - June to December 1983, 1983-06-01 - 1983-12-12; 30066054
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - April to May 1983, 1983-04-01 - 1983-05-31; 30066053
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - November 1982 to March 1983, 1982-11-03 - 1983-03-31; 01465200
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - May to October 1982, 1982-05-19 - 1982-10-27; 30066039
- South Asia Country Programs Department chronological files, 1984 - 1986; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_95-03; 0.30 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of chronological files created during Chernick's time as Senior Economist in the South Asia Country Programs Department (ASADR). The majority of the files consist of correspondence in the form of carbon copies, printed copies, and telexes. Records reflect various activities undertaken by Chernick, including: research; commenting on Bank research and policy papers and project and loan reports; writing of country program papers (CPPs); staffing of ASADR; information sharing; and seminar planning. A small number of reports are included in this series; these include: Current and Mid-Term Assessment of South Asian Countries; Indicative Statements of Economic and Sector Work for the South Asia Region; Disbursement Estimates; and Country Reports. There is, notably, a significant amount of material related to a problematic Maldives Country Report from 1986.
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - 1986, 1986-01-01 - 1986-12-31; 01465201
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - July to December 1985, 1985-07-01 - 1985-12-31; 30066056
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - January 1984 to June 1985, 1984-01-01 - 1985-06-26; 30066055
- Economic Development Institute chronological files, 1987 - 1989; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_95-04; 0.37 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of chronological files created during Chernick's time as Advisor on Senior Policy Seminars in the Economic Development Institute (EDI). The majority of the files consist of correspondence in the form of carbon copies, printed copies, and telexes; a small number of draft reports accompany the correspondence. Records primarily relate to the development and planning of Senior Policy Seminars and their evaluation. Records related to the development and planning of seminars include: correspondence with potential seminar leaders and attendees; Terms of Reference related to Chernick's trips to plan or oversee seminars; back-to-office reports; reports to other members of EDI describing planned seminars; suggestions for, and discussions of, potential seminar topics; activity briefs; and logistics. Records related to the evaluation of seminars include: Terms of Reference for Impact Evaluation of EDI activities; a draft of a seminar evaluation package; blank evaluation questionnaires; and EDI EvaluationPolicy Committee meeting records (including a report on the Committee itself [1987]).
  Other records include: a report on the World Bank Graduate Scholarship Program (1987); Chernick's proposed work program for 1987; materials related to World Bank Graduate Scholarship Program meetings; a report authored by Chernick entitled A Briefing Note on Foreign Exchange Risk (1985); reports and correspondence discussing the relationship between OED and EDI; EDI submissions to the World Bank Annual Report (submitted by Chernick); materials related to EDI Advisory Board meetings; and materials related to EDI Senior Staff meetings.
  - Sidney E. Chernick chronological files - EDI Director's Office - 1988 to 1989, 1988-01-01 - 1989-12-31; 30066058
  - Chronological file of Sidney Chernick, Advisor for EDI Senior Policy Seminars, 1987-01-01 - 1987-12-31; 01296049